Guide to the Sophia Tierong Zhu papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sophia Tierong Zhu papers
1947-2005
MS 1709
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
The papers include correspondence, writings, and photographs relating to the life and career of Sophia Tierong Zhu. Autobiographical writings about Zhu and her husband, Zhang Ifan, who were both victims of anti-rightist movements in China, comprise a substantive part of the papers. The collection also documents Zhu's close relationship with many English Language Instructors from Yale University.
Zhu, Sophia Tierong
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sophia Tierong Zhu, 1995-2001, 2003-2005; gift of Edward V. Gulick, 2000; and transfer from the Office of the President, Yale University, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
Accessions 1998-M-104 to 2003-M-083 are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
All other materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Sophia Tierong Zhu was born in Shanghai on February 6, 1915. She graduated from the University of Shanghai in 1937, with degrees in chemistry, music, and physics. On January 8, 1938, she married Zhang Ifan. After graduating from college, Zhu worked for several different social service and relief agencies in Shanghai and Changsha, including the YMCA, the YWCA, the Chinese National Relief and Rehabilitation Agency, and the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency. She died in Changsha, China, on August 9, 2009.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, writings, and photographs relating to the life and career of Sophia Tierong Zhu. Autobiographical writings about Zhu and her husband, Zhang Ifan, who were both victims of anti-rightist movements in China, comprise a substantive part of the papers. The collection also documents Zhu's close relationship with many English Language Instructors from Yale University.
In 1946, she traveled with her husband Zhang Ifan to the United States to study at Yale University, where Sophia obtained an M.A. from the Department of Sociology, and Ifan obtained a J.S.D. from the Law School in 1948. They returned to Changsha in the fall of 1948. With the victory of the People's Liberation Army and the founding of the People's Republic of China in 1949, Zhang Ifan became very involved in local and provincial politics. In 1950, Sophia began teaching English and Russian in the Department of Foreign Languages at Hunan Medical College, where she remained until her retirement in 1988.
In 1957, during the Anti-Rightist Campaign, Ifan committed suicide while suffering from diabetes and enduring severe criticism from the provincial party for advocating the idea of the rule of law over the rule of man. Soon after, Sophia was labeled an ultra-rightist. Although she was allowed to continue teaching, she was demoted from her position as chair of the department, and her pay was significantly cut. In 1965, she was labeled a special agent suspect, and she was imprisoned several times throughout the Cultural Revolution.
In 1973, she was able to resume teaching full-time. In 1979, her status as a special agent suspect and as an ultra-rightist were redressed. Shortly after, the Yale-China Association re-established ties with the Hunan Medical College. Through her position in the Department of Foreign Languages, Zhu worked closely with many of the English Language Instructors (ELIs) from Yale University who taught English at the College. In the Spring of 1988, Sophia Zhu retired from teaching, but continued to act as an advisor and resource for ELIs.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and additions: I. Correspondence, 1979-1997. II. Writings, 1950-1996. III. Photographs, 1947-1996.
China -- History -- Cultural Revolution, 1966-1976 -- Personal narratives; Zhu, Sophia Tierong; Chang, Ifan, 1906-; McDougal, Myres S. (Myres Smith), 1906-1998; Yale-China Association
- Correspondence, 1979-1997; Series I
  - B-L, 1987-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - M-Y, 1987-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brooks, Mary F., 1984-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chapman, Nancy, 1981-1983, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gulick, Edward, 1988, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Johnson, James G., 1981-1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jones, David A., 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kleinman, Jan, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lee, Frank, 1989-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Liu, Zhong Yi, 1985-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - MacDougal, John L., 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - MacDougal, Myres, 1979-1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Nuland, Drew, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pertel, Joe, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Salzman, Mark, 1987-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sheldon, Mark, 1989, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Singleton, Louise and John, 1989-1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Stepanek, Joe, 1985, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous cards and invitations, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified, 1990-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Writings, 1940-1996; Series II
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically by title or pertinent subject, the Writings series is comprised of articles, clippings, reminiscences, and teaching materials written by or about Sophia Tierong Zhu. The unpublished autobiography is excellent documentation of Zhu's life, as reported in 1988. It includes accounts of her childhood, professional career, and tribulations under anti-rightist campaigns in China. A biography of Zhang Ifan is a similar account of the life of her husband. The series also includes writings on the Yale-China Program, Yale in the late 1940s, and other family members. Most of the Unidentified material at the end of the listing is written in Chinese.
  - Autobiography, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Changsha in Action [by E.R. Lapwood], 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - China Monthly Review [articles by Sophia Zhu], 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chinese customs, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Father and Son, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fulton, Robert B. [memorial writings], 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hutchins, Francis S. [memorial writings], 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - In Memory of Edith Millican, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Life and Death, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Memories of New Haven, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Music in My Life, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - My Experience Teaching English at Hunan Medical College, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - My Life, My Work, and Changsha, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - On a New Horizon [memoir of the renewal of relations between Hunan Medical College and the Yale-China Association], 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Story of Zhang Yingfang [Zhu's grandson], 1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Teaching Materials, 1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Zhang Ifan
    - Biography of Zhang Ifan, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Published biographical material, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Photographs, 1947-1996; Series III
  - American friends, 1972, 1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American friends from pre-1949 period, 1939, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Childhood and college years, 1930-1937, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Cultural revolution, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Family pictures, 1950-1994, undated (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Hunan Medical College, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Relief work, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Yale University, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Yale-China Association
    - Bachelors/ELIs
      - 1980s (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
      - 1990s (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Changsha
      - YCA's return, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - YCA staff visits, 1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Additional Material, Accession 1998-M-093
  The addition includes a small amount of correspondence, writings, and photographs which continue the documentation in the main accession of the life of Sophia Zhu. Most of the correspondence is from former English Language Instructors. The photographs also depict ELIs with their families.
  - Correspondence, B-Y, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reminiscences [misc.], 1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional material, Accession 1998-M-104
  Also includes Accessions 1998-M-124, 1999-M-034, and 1999-M-060.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
  - Additional material (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-134 (Box 1)
  Includes accession 2002-M-037.
- Additional Material, Accession 2001-M-039 (Box 1)
  Includes accession 2001-M-079.
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-083 (Box 1)
  Includes accessions 2005-M-045 and 2006-M-024.